IRVING GÓMEZ MÉNDEZ





Summary

I am a mathematician that merges the experience in applied statistics and data science with a solid theoretical background in statistics (Regression, Inference, Multivariate Analysis, Bayesian Statistics, etc.) and machine learning (Random Forests, Neural Networks, Support Vector Machines, Recommender Systems, etc.) who enjoys passing from theory to development of meaningful tech products.

A portfolio of past and current projects, talks and courses can be found at https://irvinggomez.com while their respective codes can be found at https://github.com/IrvingGomez.

Computing Skills

Programming Languages: Python, Julia, R

Data Visualization: Plotly, Tableau, Shiny, Ggplot2

Deep Learning: TensorFlow Big Data: Pyspark

Other Data Analysis: SPSS, Google Analytics Other Languages: SQL, HTML, CSS, LATEX

Professional Experience

National Electronics and Computer Technology Center (NECTEC), Thailand Postdoctoral Researcher

March 2023 - To date

• Analysis of data and deployment of artificial intelligence for monitoring and evaluating national strategy and country reforms.

Universidad Iberoamericana (Ibero-American University)

Lecturer

August 2021 - To date

- Development and improvement of actuarial subjects' syllabus.
- Teaching undergraduate subjects.

Bayesian Statistics 2022 - 2023 Machine Learning 2021 - 2022 Actuarial Probability 2021

Banco del Bajío (Bajio Bank)

Sr. Data Scientist

July 2021 - February 2023

- Improvement of statistical tools for internal fraud detection.
- Development of end-to-end projects to evaluate prospects' credit risk.
- Present results and projects' progress on an executive level.
- Translate business and customer needs to technical language to determine the best model and solution.
- Data wrangling and feature engineering from large databases, merging public and private information sources of heterogeneous data.
- Implementation and evaluation of algorithms to estimate the stability of economic sectors.
- Robust statistical inference to improve prospects' estimations.

- Geo-statistical analysis to help in decision making.
- Data mining for marketing campaigns and cybersecurity projects.
- Implementation of models in an AutoML framework.

Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (Center for Research in Mathematics, CIMAT)

Postgraduate Student in Probability and Statistics

August 2014 - June 2021

- Development and implementation of state-of-the-art random forests algorithms to handle data with missing values.
- Implementation of neural networks for recommender systems with partial information.

 Research stay at Inria Lille-Nord Europe, France.
- Development of methodologies for detection of illegal traffic of species in America.

 Interdisciplinary workshop at Center for Research and Advanced Studies of the National Polytechnic Institute (Cinvestav).
- Implementation of methodologies for control quality with heavily censored data.
- Statistical consulting for the automotive industry, improving its warranty management. Industrial workshop at CIMAT.
- Reliability analysis for the food industry, increasing preference of consumers. Industrial workshop at CIMAT.
- Teaching assistant in undergraduate and graduate subjects. Statistical Inference 2015 - 2019 Statistical Models 2017 - 2019, 2021

OPI Analytics

Sr. Data Scientist

August 2020 - December 2020

- Development and improvement of end-to-end projects for sale's forecasts.
- Monitor and validation of building blocks.
- Automation of data science processes.
- Validation of pricing strategies.

Academic Qualifications

PhD in Probability and Statistics
Research stay
Actively Querying Missing Information Using Neural Networks, in collaboration with Dr. Jill-Jênn Vie
MSc in Probability and Statistics Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (CIMAT), Guanajuato, Mexico
Mathematical Engineer
Exchange Student

David Sprott Award, 2015

Annual prize granted by the Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (CIMAT) to the best master's exam in the area of statistics.

Publications

Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Emilien Joly (2023a). "On the consistency of a random forest algorithm in the presence of missing entries". In: *Journal of Nonparametric Statistics*. DOI: 10.1080/10485252.2023.2219783.

Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Emilien Joly (2023b). "Regression with missing data, a comparison study of techniques based on random forests". In: *Journal of Statistical Computation and Simulation*. DOI: 10.1080/00949655.2022. 2163646.

Selected Talks

01/2022

Mathematical Association of Cambodia (MAC), Virtual $An\ Introduction\ to\ Causality$

12/2020

Hispanohablante Seminar, Guanajuato

Consistency of a Random Forest Algorithm with Missing Entries

03/2020

Inria Sequel Seminar, Lille

Some ideas for random forests with missing values 01/2020

TRIPODS workshop CIMAT-University of Arizona, Guanajuato

Some ideas for random forests with missing values

Certifications

Google Analytics
Data Sets with SQL
SQL for Data Science
Statistical Analysis with SPSS

Languages

Spanish Native
Portuguese Fluent
English Fluent
French Basic
Russian Basic

Thai Elemental (learning)